Guide to the Dante Gabriel Rossetti Letters to Ellen Heaton
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Dante Gabriel Rossetti Letters to Ellen Heaton
1855-1875
MSS.47
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
.42
1 box
The collection comprises 57 letters from Dante Gabriel Rossetti to Ellen Heaton written from 1855 to 1875 (the bulk from 1855 to 1864). The letters primarily pertain to works by Rossetti, including a number of his works commissioned by Heaton. Works referenced include: Beata Beatrix, Beloved, Bethlehem Gate, Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice, Dante's vision of Rachel and Leah, How Sir Galahad, Sir Bors and Sir Percival were fed with the Sanct Grael; but Sir Percival's sister died by the way, Joan of Arc, Mary in the house of St. John, Salutation of Beatrice, and St. George and the Princess Sabra. The letters reflect Heaton's reputation as an important collector and patron. Rossetti recommends (and, in some instances, requests) that she acquire work by many other artists associated with the Pre-Raphaelites, including Arthur Hughes, William Holman Hunt and Ford Maddox Brown.
Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882
Biographical / Historical
Dante Gabriel Rossetti (1828-1882) was an English poet, painter and translator. Born in London, Rossetti hailed from an artistically prodigious family; his Italian father was a Dante scholar while his sister, Christina Rossetti, became a renowned romantic poet and his brother, William Michael, an accomplished writer and critic. Like many members of the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood, Rossetti received his early artistic training at Sass's Drawing Academy, London, entering the school probably in 1841. In 1848, alongside William Holman Hunt, John Everett Millais and others, Rossetti founded the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood, a group of English painters, poets and critics. The Pre-Raphaelites sought to reform British art through a return to honest simplicity and the use of luminous colors and literary themes. Rossetti and the Pre-Raphaelites advocated for "truth to nature" in art, their work reflecting a mimesis of nature, rich detail and influences from Quattrocento Italian art. The Pre-Raphaelites received praise and endorsement from the influential art critic John Ruskin who boldly predicted that the Pre-Raphaelites would "lay in our land the foundations of a school of art nobler than has been seen for three hundred years" (Ruskin letter to The Times, 30 May 1851). Rossetti's Girlhood of Mary Virgin (1849) was the first work to be exhibited carrying the Brotherhood's initials. In addition to his drawing and paintings, Rossetti was a prolific writer, publishing many of his own poems and sonnets and producing a number of translations of Italian medieval poetry, including that of Dante Alighieri.
The recipient of the letters, Ellen Heaton (1816-1894), was a Leeds based art collector and philanthropist. Heaton began collecting art after inheriting a significant amount of money and property following the deaths of her parents. Heaton's attention was first drawn to Rossetti's work by John Ruskin, a friend of Heaton's and someone from whom she often sought art collecting advice. Heaton was among the first to commission work by Rossetti and patronized, or considered patronizing, work by other artists associated with the Pre-Raphaelites, including Arthur Hughes, J.W. Inchbold and Edward Burne-Jones. Heaton was often referred to as having had a unique personality. In an 1863 letter to his father, Ruskin wrote, "Miss Heaton is – Miss Heaton, and always will be" (Sublime and Instructive, 151). Heaton was friendly with a number of writers and artists of her era, including Elizabeth Barrett Browning and Robert Browning. Heaton never married. She traveled extensively throughout Great Britain and Europe, often with her domestic partner, Fanny Haworth. In addition to her direct support of artists through commissioned paintings and drawings, Heaton engaged in acts of cultural philanthropy, including providing the financial means for working men to attend lectures and supporting impoverished lace artisans in Leeds.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection
Arrangement
The letters are arranged chronologically. Item numbering corresponds to that given in Fredeman, The correspondence of Dante Gabriel Rossetti.
Existence and Location of Copies
The letters are transcribed in their entirety, with annotations, in: The correspondence of Dante Gabriel Rossetti. Edited by William E. Fredeman. Woodbridge, Suffolk, UK; Rochester, NY: D.S. Brewer, 2002-2009.
See: http://hdl.handle.net/10079/bibid/5982726
Related Materials
Related material: John Ruskin Letters to Ellen Heaton (MSS 46), Yale Center for British Art, Department of Rare Books and Manuscripts.
Custodial History
The material passed from Ellen Heaton to her nephew John Heaton, and subsequently to his brother Beresford Heaton, then to Katherine Ogilvy Heaton, and finally to Elizabeth Maud Sackville Robertson. Sold at auction, Christie, Manson & Woods, July 16, 1969 (see catalog entry no. 117).
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises 57 letters from Dante Gabriel Rossetti to Ellen Heaton written from 1855 to 1875 (the bulk from 1855 to 1864). The letters primarily pertain to works by Rossetti, including a number of his works commissioned by Heaton. Works referenced include: Beata Beatrix, Beloved, Bethlehem Gate, Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice, Dante's vision of Rachel and Leah, How Sir Galahad, Sir Bors and Sir Percival were fed with the Sanct Grael; but Sir Percival's sister died by the way, Joan of Arc, Mary in the house of St. John, Salutation of Beatrice, and St. George and the Princess Sabra. The letters reflect Heaton's reputation as an important collector and patron. Rossetti recommends (and, in some instances, requests) that she acquire work by many other artists associated with the Pre-Raphaelites, including Arthur Hughes, William Holman Hunt and Ford Maddox Brown.
Rossetti's financial conduct and affairs are made apparent through his detailed instructions for Heaton regarding payment methods and frequency, his justifications for the price of works and his commentary on associations with art dealers and other patrons, including Thomas Plint, Walter Dunlop and the influential art critic John Ruskin. In addition to his business dealings, these letters offer insights into Rossetti's artistic process. In one letter, Rossetti expresses his relative displeasure for painting specially commissioned subjects, which often "never interested" him, and articulates his preference for painting subjects of his own devising (1856 March 12). Also evident in the correspondence is Rossetti's penchant for frequently altering his drawings and paintings, a trait which, in a letter to Ellen Heaton, Ruskin complained often resulted in these works developing "odd faults" (John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 November 8). Rossetti's motivations behind his artistic decisions and alterations are described. For instance, Rossetti justifies his alteration of the size of Dante's feet in Dante's Dream on the Day of the Death of Beatrice as correcting their previous state of "being (I know not by what hallucination of my part) of the canoe class in shape and size" (1863 November 21). Another letter conveys his impatience to amend the "incautious use of red lead" in St. George and the Princess Sabra (1863 June 25).
Rossetti expounds upon his thoughts on art and literature, recommending particular exhibitions, texts and works to Heaton. He encourages her to visit an 1856 exhibition of William Ward, Earl of Dudley's collection at the Egyptian Hall, London and – in the same year – recommends the works of Giotto on display at the Crystal Palace, London as the "finest sacred art I ever saw" (1856 May 12). The letters also convey the importance placed by Rossetti upon the contemporary British artistic and literary cultural scene and record his musings about his place within it. Rossetti makes frequent references to his and Heaton's mutual friends, Robert and Elizabeth Barrett Browning, and gives his opinion that their writing is "glorious" and "almost beyond anything for exhaustless poetic resource," respectively (1865 November 13 and 1856 November 21). Rossetti explicates his philosophy that, while admiring the work of his contemporaries, he does not believe that artists should depict literary scenes created by writers working in their own period, remarking that he "never illustrate[s] modern writers as a rule, though once or twice I have done so with Browning only, from especial love of him. Such mingling of contemporary ideas is like the intermarriage of the same families, sure to lead to degeneracy" (1863 May 22).
Rossetti makes frequent reference to John Ruskin, who initially introduced Heaton to Rossetti's work. The important role played by Ruskin in facilitating the relationships between the Pre-Raphaelites and their patrons is apparent; often, Rossetti desires Ruskin to view and approve of his completed works before sending them on to Heaton. In the second letter in the series, Rossetti expresses his indebtedness to Ruskin for first drawing Heaton's attention to his work.
The correspondence also reveals the increasingly prominent role played by photography in documenting and distributing art as well as the limitations of the technology available. Rossetti frequently responds to Heaton's requests to have works photographed with the opinion that the subject in question will not photograph well. At one stage, Rossetti proclaims the attempt to photograph Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice as a "bogie with a vengeance," bemoaning the darkening of one side of the image, arising as a result of "bungling."
In some of the letters, sections of the page have been removed. These are often pieces containing Rossetti's crest and monograph, or his autograph signature. Presumably, Heaton wished to preserve these especially and in one letter Rossetti begrudgingly agrees to send samples of his signature to her, despite his "real horror of autography" (1863 November 21).
Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art appreciation; Painters -- Great Britain; Painting, British -- 19th century; Photography; Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 ( Correspondence); Ashburton, Louisa, Lady, 1827-1903; Barrett, Arabella, -1868; Brown, Ford Madox, 1821-1893; Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321; Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915; Hunt, William Holman, 1827-1910; Millais, John Everett, 1829-1896; Morris, Jane, 1839-1914; Plint, Ellen, -1861; Plint, Thomas Edward, 1823-1861; Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood; Rose, James Anderson, 1819-1890; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 ( Beata Beatrix); Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 ( Beloved); Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 ( Bethlehem Gate); Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 ( Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice); Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 ( Dante's vision of Rachel and Leah); Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 ( How Sir Galahad, Sir Bors and Sir Percival were fed with the Sanct Grael; but Sir Percival's sister died by the way); Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 ( Joan of Arc); Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 ( Mary in the house of St. John); Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 ( Salutation of Beatrice); Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 ( St. George and the Princess Sabra); Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain); Seddon, Thomas, 1821-1856; Siddall, Elizabeth; Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, Baron, 1809-1892
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 February 6; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 55.7)
  General
  With envelope. Addressed from 14 Chatham Place, Blackfriars. With black mourning border.
  Scope and Contents
  Rossetti accepts Heaton's commission but asks whether, if he is unable to find complementary Dante subjects for two different works, he could produce one, larger work for no more than 40 guineas. Rossetti says he has already drawn a number of small Dante subjects and is worried he might not find new inspiration from Dante for small works. Rossetti describes works in progress depicting Dante and Beatrice, saying "they would execute well ... in water colour." Rossetti remarks that he has known a Dr. Hare for some time and says that he is indebted to John Ruskin for first drawing Rossetti to the attention of Heaton.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Hare, Charles John, 1818-1898; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 February 27?; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 55.11)
  With envelope; black mourning border. Date provided by Fredeman.
  Rossetti says that "owing to absence," Heaton's letter has only just reached him. Rossetti provides Heaton with Arthur Hughes's address and describes Hughes as "the one ... whose genius is, beyond a doubt, of the highest order." He says that he thinks Heaton would admire his works' "genuine poetry and originality." Rossetti ends by apologizing for the hastiness of his response, explaining he is busy with work.
  Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 May 11; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 55.23)
  Addressed from 14 Chatham Place. Date provided by Fredeman.
  Rossetti expresses his hope that he can begin Heaton's commission and tells her that he will write to her if he commences the work while she is still in London so that she can visit him to see it. Rossetti admits that the "interruptions" delaying his work on Heaton's commission have also held up his other pieces and so he does not have anything "to show at present" but thanks Heaton for her continued interest. Rossetti is pleased that a gentleman has commissioned work from Arthur Hughes on Heaton's recommendation.
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 November 24; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autogrpah letter signed; 17 x 21 cm, folded to 17 x 10 cm (Box 1, Folder 55.57)
  With envelope. Addressed from 14 Chatham Place, Blackfriars.
  Rossetti explains that he has been in Paris for the past ten days and so only just received Heaton's latest letter. Rossetti has heard from Ruskin that Heaton would prefer keeping the drawing from the Purgatorio of Rachel and Leah, or Matilda and Beatrice. Rossetti remarks that he has given Matilda and Beatrice the actions of Rachel and Leah and describes the two figures as "of an entirely Oriental character, as the real Rachel and Leah would be." Rossetti thanks Heaton for her second commission and tells her that he did not expect to be in Paris so long or her would have arranged to have his letters forwarded to him there. Rossetti thinks that the Exhibition of Pictures "does us [the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood?] credit" and praises the merits of exhibited works by Millais, Hunt and "Lewis and Leslie." Rossetti compliments the work of Eugène Delacroix, Jean-Auguste-Dominique Ingres and Kraus (Georg Melchior Kraus?). Rossetti admits that, like Heaton, he wishes Ruskin had attended the exhibition. Rossetti says he spent much of his time in Paris with the Brownings and passes on their kind regards to Heaton. Rossetti describes Robert Browning's "Men and Women" as "a glorious book."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's vision of Rachel and Leah; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861; Millais, John Everett, 1829-1896; Hunt, William Holman, 1827-1910; Leslie, George Dunlop, 1835-1921; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 March 12; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 2 folded sheets (4, and 3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.12)
  Addressed from 14 Chatham Place, Blackfriars Bridge.
  Rossetti tells Heaton that he is happy to make any changes she wishes to her commissioned drawing ( Rachel and Leah ) and instructs her on how to send it back to him. Rossetti admits he received Heaton's papers from Leeds but that he hadn't wanted to reply until he had some further information regarding her commission. Rossetti explains that he is more than half way towards completing a work depicting Dante's dream of Beatrice lying dead. He mentions that Ruskin has seen the partially completed piece and "seemed much pleased with it." Rossetti quotes the lines from Dante's Vita Nuova which inspire the piece and describes the work in detail, stating that "it is in every respect a much better drawing than [ Rachel and Leah ].". Rossetti admits that because the Rachel and Leah piece was commissioned, the subject "never interested" him. He tells Heaton that, as the work is now larger than first intended, the price will be 50 guineas but that he understands if Heaton cannot now purchase the work, the price being 10 guineas higher than previously agreed. Rossetti goes on to justify the price by saying that it is the usual asking price for his works and that Ruskin commissioned a much smaller piece from him for the same sum. Rossetti asks, if Heaton still wishes to commission the piece, to send him £20 "on account of it" or, if she no longer wants the work, to let him know as soon as is possible.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's vision of Rachel and Leah; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 March 14; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.13)
  With envelope. Date from Fredeman.
  Rossetti tells Heaton that he has received the half of a £20 note. He has also received Rachel and Leah and tells Heaton he will have it framed. Rossetti admits that he does not know what works Millais is sending to the Royal Academy. He says that Ruskin has not seen his most recent work since it was about a third done as Rossetti asked Ruskin to wait to view it until it was finished. He says that he has not altered it "more than is unavoidable" and that it will be finished and framed before Heaton is next in town. Rossetti has not heard about the meeting at the Architectural Museum and apologizes that he cannot give Heaton the information she requested of him.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's vision of Rachel and Leah; Millais, John Everett, 1829-1896; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 April 12; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.23)
  With envelope.
  Rossetti thanks Heaton for £30 she has sent him towards her commissioned drawing(s) worth 40 or 50 guineas. He assures her that he needed the money otherwise he would not have petitioned Ruskin to ask her for an advance. Rossetti describes ideas he has for drawings, including one of the Virgin Mary in the house of St. John after the crucifixion, stating that the motto on the frame could be "A little while and ye shall not see me, and again a little while ye shall see me." He describes the subject as "melancholy" and says he has two "modern" subjects which possess a "more happy aspect." Rossetti says he hopes Heaton will like his present drawing as much as Ruskin does and tells Heaton he will write to her once it is completed.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Mary in the house of St. John; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 April 22; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.26)
  Rossetti tells Heaton that he delayed sending her drawing as he has not received a response from Ruskin and that he had made appointments with friends to view it. He says that the drawing's packing case is prepared and that the drawing should be ready for transportation as soon as Ruskin replies. Rossetti says he has still to decide whether to make Heaton's latest commission one or two drawings and will not know until he has finished one drawing when he will know whether to produce another. Rossetti says he hopes he will be able to make Heaton a sketch of The Virgin and St John and that he hopes to see Heaton in the forthcoming Friday as he has a previously arranged appointment on Wednesday. Rossetti mentions that an old friend of his, Edward Bateman, was an acquaintance of Heaton's, remarking that he fears Bateman's "talents must be very much wasted on the Australians."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Mary in the house of St. John; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Bateman, Edward La Trobe, approximately 1815-1897; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 April 23; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.27)
  "I write one word to say that the drawing has gone to Oxford to Mr. Ruskin, though I am not sure it will be in time to catch him. In either case, I have arranged that it shall be sent back to me almost immediately."
  Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 April 25; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 22 cm, folded to 19 x 11 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.28)
  With envelope. Addressed from 14 Chatham Place.
  "The drawing has been to Oxford, and is just back -- I suspect unfortunately without catching Mr. Ruskin. Will fix a day and hour most suitable to you after Monday, when you can see it. If equally pleasing to you, I would like to keep it by me a few days yet, that one or two friends may see it." In a postscript, Rossetti asks if the time Heaton choses is unsuitable for him whether he might be able to suggest another time. Rossetti tells Heaton that, although she would like to see his work, he only has two drawings in progress and that one of them has been borrowed by Ruskin.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence